It appears the class is still enjoying
spring break.
We have
barely 40 people in class.
All right, let's begin.
Uh, I'm assuming the others will join
and thank you all for the understanding
of the break.
I hope you had a good spring break.
We're going to pick up our series of
lectures on recurrent neural networks.
So can anybody remind me what the last
thing we discussed was? Anyone?
What was the last thing we discussed?
LSTMs and GRUs. Right. So
here was a summary of everything we've
seen so far. We saw that recurrent
structures can be trained. Recurrent
structures are good for modeling time
series. they can be applied not just for
time series problems but also for other
problems where they can uh provide
sufficiently I mean surprisingly
efficient solutions.
We saw that recurrence structures can be
trained by minimizing the divergence
between the sequence of outputs that the
model generates and the desired sequence
of outputs.
we must define a divergence between the
two and then the network can be trained
through gradient descent and back
propagation.
The challenge here is to define the
divergence between sequences because as
we saw when you're outputting a sequence
and the desired output is also a
sequence there is no uh requirement
there is no guarantee that there is any
kind of onetoone correspondence between
what the network outputs and what you
desire it to output.
So we also saw that networks can have
many variants. Recurrent networks can
have many variants. Your simple standard
conventional MLP
that is also capable of analyzing time
series data. Although the model itself
doesn't have recurrence inside it. The
more standard recurrent network that we
saw in the previous weeks was this one
to the right where the input is a
sequence and the output is also a
sequence and there's a onetoone
correspondence between inputs and
outputs. So corresponding to each input
there is an output.
We could also have other kinds of uh
records where you analyze an entire
sequence of inputs and then make a
prediction. So this you might per you do
for instance in simple speech
recognition problems or in sentiment
analysis for question answer. Then here
is a more interesting one. This is going
to be the focus of uh the next couple of
lectures where the input is a sequence.
The output is also a sequence but then
there is no one toone correspondence
between the input and the output. So the
outputs are intermittent.
It's not that the output is is uh the
the order of the output is unrelated to
the order of the input. So for example,
if you took this group of inputs and
this group of inputs and swap them swap
their locations, then the outputs over
here would also change accordingly. So
there is an order correspondence
between the outputs and the inputs. But
there is no time correspondence. There's
no one toone correspondence between the
inputs and the outputs. This make sense
to you guys? I'm speaking of order
synchrony but no time synchrony.
Right? So this is the kind of problem
we're going to be looking at. Then of
course you can have other kinds of
problems where you analyze an entire
input and then generate an entire
output. We mentioned examples of
problems where this applies. Anybody
remember one such example? What kind of
problem where would use this model?
Anybody?
Translation, right? And here's another
one where a single input generates an
entire sequence of outputs. What kind of
problem did we say? Uh image captioning,
right? So let's look at the most simple
version first. the MLP
here we're going to have an output for
every input because every input is
immediately processed and generates an
output. Nevertheless, we can use it to
analyze time series. How so? The input
would be a time series and corresponding
to each input the model would produce an
output. So observe that the manner in
which it processes the input at any time
is unrelated to how it processes the
input at any other time. So the
processing over here has no influence on
the processing over here. So how then
does this capture the time series nature
of data? That's going to be through the
divergence.
So this model just the MLP can analyze a
time series input and generate one
output for every input. Your desired
output is also going to be a sequence.
You can now define a divergence between
the desired output and the actual output
of the network. And the derivatives are
going to be of this divergence over
sequences. And it is the derivative the
divergence is going to be a divergence
over sequences. And it is the derivative
of this divergence
over sequences that is going to be used
to train the network. So although the
model is just a simple MLP, it can
nevertheless be used as a not very
effective but nonetheless
possible model for analyzing time
series. So here how would you actually
capture the time series nature of the
problem? This is through the divergence.
You're going to have a sequence of
outputs, a sequence of desired outputs.
You define a divergence between these
two sequences.
And it's the derivative of this
divergence that is back propagated.
This divergence must have a derivative
with respect to each of these outputs
for back propagation to work. Now a very
common assumption that we will make is
that the divergence between two
sequences can be decomposed
into the sum of divergences at each
time. For this to work, there must be a
one:one correspondence between the
actual and desired outputs of the
network. In that case, the divergence
between two sequences is going to simply
be the sum over time
of the divergences at each time. And so
now when you compute the derivative of
the divergence with respect to any
output, it's sufficient to compute the
derivative of the local divergence at
that time with respect to that output
and that is what is going to be back
propagated. So did all of that make
sense? How we could use MLPS
to model time series and uh what the
simple assumpt approximation that we can
make simplifying assumption that we can
make to simplify how divergences can be
differentiated.
So that leads us to our very first poll.
Here you go.
10 seconds, guys.
All right, let me stop this one.
What is the answer to the first
question? True or false? True. Second
one,
this says also true. Right? Sure enough.
Conventional MLPS too can be used to
model sequences. When we use
conventional MLPS to model sequences,
the sequence nature of the problem is
captured through the divergence which is
now computed between the output sequence
and the desired output sequence. This is
not a very effective model for sequences
but can nonetheless be used to analyze
time series data.
But then let's look at the more
important problem. This is going to be
our base problem base model where you
analyze a time series. You generate a
time series and there is a strict one to
one correspondence between the inputs
and the outputs. Meaning for every input
there is an output. So this is what we
will call a timesynchronous model. It's
times synchronous because for every
input there is an output.
And the nice thing about this model is
that all the math is very simple and
more importantly every other problem can
be reduced to some variant of this basic
model. So that's why this is going to be
the prime focus.
Here you would have a sequence of inputs
corresponding to each input there would
be an output
mind you so one such example is
assigning grammar tags to words in a
sentence you'd analyze a sequence of
words you'd assign a grammar tag to
every word the processing itself could
be unidirectional left to right or
birectional going both ways regardless
the fact is
the there is one output for every input.
It doesn't matter whether you analyze it
just strictly left to right or or
birectional.
The uh the key point is that the outputs
have a time correspondence with the
input.
Now for my for my lecture I'm going to
continue assuming one unidirectional
processing.
But you must keep in mind that
everything that I say for unidirectional
processing also holds for birectional
models because the directionality of the
processing is not going to be the focus
of this lecture.
So in this case once again what do we
do? The model generates a sequence of
outputs. Again because there's a
onetoone correspondence between outputs
and inputs there will be as many outputs
as there are inputs. And so the
divergence that we compute is going to
be the divergence between the desired
output sequence and the actual output
sequence. Now once again
for in order to train the model this
divergence must be differentiated and so
we need the derivative of this
divergence with respect to each of these
outputs in order for for us to be able
to train the model.
The challenge is how do we compute this
divergence? And one very simple
assumption we can make is that there is
a onetoone correspondence between the
desired output sequence and the actual
output sequence. Mind you, this is not
necessarily true. So the desired output
sequence could have an entirely
different length than the actual output
sequence, but that causes all kinds of
problems. And so we will try to reduce
it to the case where the desired output
sequence has as many symbols as the
actual output sequence which in turn is
exactly as long as the input. In this
case, I can now redefine my divergence
over these two sequences as the sum over
time of the divergences at individual
tops. And the kind and the type of
divergence that we compute at individual
times is most commonly the kale
divergence between the actual output of
the network at any time and the target
at the same time. So, did all of this
make sense
what we've said so far? Okay.
So, that leads us to our second book.
10 seconds, guys.
Okay, let me ed
answers.
What are the answers?
1 and three,
right? There's one output corresponding
to every input.
They
can be birectional and the divergence
between the true and desired outputs can
have an additive contribution from the
output at each time. So this model over
here is the one we like. But proceeding
from there, let's take a look at other
kinds of models like this one over here.
So here is a model where you analyze an
entire
uh input sequence and produce a single
output at the end of it. So this could
be for example if I'm performing simple
speech recognition where I look at an
entire input recording and tell you
whether this includes the word uh CD or
not or uh a sentiment analysis problem
where I look at the entire input and
then tell you whether the sentiment of
the simple sentence is positive or
negative. I have to wait for the entire
input because the entire sentiment could
be modified by just one word at the end
which negates everything. So you cannot
actually begin making statements till
you've seen the entire sequence. So
this model is what we'll start off
looking at again problems like speech
recognition, question answering or
sentiment analysis. The output answer is
at the end of the input.
This could be for question answering or
speech recognition. I'm going to be
using speech recognition as an example
through these two lectures because one
of the most important problems where
these models are used is speech
recognition. Again, if you were trying
to recognize phone names, you would
analyze the entire sequence of input
speech vectors and at the end you would
decide whether it was an R or an E or
any other phone name.
So here, how would you perform
inference?
You get your input sequence. You just
analyze the input sequence
and at the end of the input sequence,
the network is going to generate not a
single output. It's actually going to
generate a probability vector where it
computes a probability for every
possible symbol in the vocabulary. And
if you had to perform classification,
you pick the symbol for which the
probability was highest.
But then so that make sense to
everybody.
How this work? Yes or no? Okay. But what
happens at these terms?
I'm getting an output at the end of the
input. What happens at these times?
Anyone?
What do you think happens at these
times? Waiting, storing. So the model is
not the remember it's the same model
being applied at every time. So the
model in fact continues to generate
outputs at each time.
What we did was to ignore these two
outputs and only read the final output.
But because the model is the same at
every time the model actually does
generate outputs, we ignore them. That
make sense to everybody?
Yes or no? Okay.
And that makes for a lot of very
interesting stuff that will come later
in this lecture. So when I want to train
the model, I'd get an input. I'd pass
the input sequence through the model. It
it would generate an output probability
vector at the very end and I'd have the
target symbol. I can compute the
divergence between these two and I can
back propagate that divergence, the
derivatives of the divergence through
the network to train the model.
But then is this the most effective
thing? Is there something more I could
do? over here.
Any ideas on how I could improve on
this?
Any ideas?
Any thoughts?
The shortcoming is that you're you're
ignoring these two outputs. Correct?
We don't need to ignore these two
outputs.
If
in the case of particularly in the case
of speech recognition, right? If it's an
R over here, it's probably an R
everywhere. And even in the case of
sentiment analysis, the sentiment
doesn't always change dramatically at
the end. It builds up over the sentence,
right? So these guys too carry positive
useful signatures of the performance of
the model. And so what you can do is to
assume that the target label over here
is the same label that should have been
applied at every one of these time
instance. And now your overall
divergence is going to be the sum
of the divergences over every single
output. And so instead of just getting a
single signal from here, now we're going
to sum over all time. And the actual
divergence is going to be a weighted sum
of the divergences at each time. This is
what you differentiate to train the
model. This make sense to everybody?
Yes. No.
Okay. And so easy enough.
Now, what are these weights?
If you're performing speech recognition,
it makes sense to assume that if this is
an R, it's always an R. On the other
hand, if you're doing something like
question answering where the keyword
comes at the end, then you probably
don't want to be considering these guys.
So these guys would have weight zero.
This would have weight one. But the
simplest case, it's it's easiest to
assume that every one of these things
provides the same amount of information
to train the model as everything else.
So these weights would all be one.
So I think did that answer your
question?
I assume so. Right.
So I assume everybody understood this
model over here. Now let's switch to the
more interesting model. This guy is your
order synchronous but time asynchronous
model. Here you analyze an input
sequence and then you produce outputs
intermittently. You're not producing
outputs at every time. You just produce
outputs intermittently.
But this little change. So this model is
not really very different from this
model. This guy is simply like many
copies of this guy attached to one
another. That small change makes things
a whole lot more complicated and a whole
lot more interesting. Let's see how.
Right now you're given a sequence of
inputs
and you want to output symbols
intermittently.
So as we saw this is just a simple
concatenation of many copies of this
model.
What is the complication that arises
from this?
I'm giving you this entire sequence x1
through xn x9 here x0 through x9 and I
want to intermittently generate outputs.
What is the complication that arises
through this
where we've just taken many copies of
this guy? Anybody?
What would the complication be?
Where does each
remember the model itself generates
outputs at every time, right?
So, we don't know which of these outputs
to read. Nobody told us which of these
outputs one must read. So, here you have
outputs coming at every time. And
somehow magically you must determine
that the outputs to read are this guy,
this guy and this guy. And that makes
things very complicated because we don't
know when to read the output. So
again,
how do how what is the inference
problem? The model generates a
probability vector at each time and
somehow magically we must figure out
that these
are the ones that are relevant and these
are the ones that we must read. So again
when you read this you're actually
making an implicit assumption. When
you're reading something over here this
guy is representing this entire segment.
Now to
enforce this idea, let's go back and
look at this model over here. Over here,
you read an entire sequence and
generated an output. So this output
didn't just represent this latest input.
It represented the entire sequence. So
also when I go over here and decide to
read the outputs here, here and here,
this guy that I read over here
represents this entire sequence. This
guy represents this entire sequence.
This guy represents this entire
sequence. The key is that I've read the
outputs at these three locations. That
make sense to everybody that I'm only
reading three outputs, but each of them
actually represents an entire segment of
the output. Right?
And the question is where do I read
these outputs?
Now to read that to figure this out we
have to go back and look at what we
actually do when we perform inference
with a neural network. When you perform
inference with a neural network at the
end of the inference the model actually
gives you the a posterior probabilities
for all the classes. That's what your
softmax gives you. Right? And so when
you want to perform classification, when
you want to choose a specific class, you
choose the class for which this
probability is highest. So you perform
maximum a posteriority probability
classification. Meaning you pick the
class that has the highest aosterior
probability. A posterior because it's
the probability assigned to the class
after seeing the data. Posterior to
seeing the data. So this is the standard
principle when we use neural networks
for classification. We are going to use
the same principle over here. So in
other words, there are many different
combinations that I can read here at the
network is generating an entire vector
of outputs at each time. I could be
choosing to read this symbol, this
symbol, this symbol and this guy. Or I
could be choosing to read this symbol,
this one, and this one. Right? There are
many different combinations of symbol,
not order synchronous, but time
asynchronous symbol sequences that I
could choose. And the maximum
aposteriority principle says that I must
choose the sequence that has the highest
aposteriority probability given the
input.
That make sense?
to everybody what do you want to do
so Bruno there is no prior you're
directly computing the posteriors so did
this did this make sense what we're
trying to do right
and so we might the challenge is how do
we choose them right and let's get to
that now again the thing is that when I
choose this
and say this and This
each of these guys is not just
representing one input. This guy is
representing this entire sequence. So
this guy is representing this entire
sequence. This guy is representing this
entire sequence. I could make it more
more explicit by saying instead of just
having a D over here, I can say D and D.
I can make this E E and E. I can make
this A and U. Right? That's just making
the fact that this guy is representing
this entire duration explicit by writing
D
and D and writing E and E and R and R
and that make sense to everybody
that this is just making the selection
of symbols at each time explicit. So
you can sort of build your entire
inference on this uh observation. What
you can do a simple greedy mechanism is
to select the most probable symbol at
each time and then once you select the
most probable symbol at each time then
subsequently you can merge repetitions
and say all of these collapse to a
single f being output at this time. All
of these collapse to a single E being
output at this time. These two guys
collapse to a single G output at this
time.
So this makes sense what I'm doing.
Okay. So what would the problem with
this something like this be?
What would the problem with something
like this be?
anyone?
How do we know
repetitions? That's the problem. Look at
this guy, right? Does this
actually have two Fs or is it just one
extended F? There's no way of saying,
right, we need some way of
distinguishing
repetitions from one single long
sequence. And this mechanism does not
provide that.
The key over here however is to do some
to observe something interesting. What I
did over here is to convert an order
synchronous but time asynchronous
inference problem to a time synchronous
inference problem. What I mean by time
synchronous is that I I obtained an
output at every time and then collapse
them into an order synchronous output.
That make sense that I've actually
performed a time-s inference and
collapsed the time synchronous output to
an order synchronous output.
That that make sense to everybody?
Yes or no? Okay.
But and so and this is one way of doing
it. But this has a problem. It doesn't
actually allow us to rep identify
repetitions.
Also, the stuff that you get can be
complete garbage. I mean what's feed
right? There's no constraint over here
telling you what makes sense and what
does not.
So you can try to improve on that. You
can try to improve ex impose external
constraints where I say that although
I'm still computing this time
synchronous inference the kinds of
sequences that I allow must map onto
something I know like dictionary words
or I could use a special separating
symbol to separate repetitions. We'll
see that in the next class. Regardless,
we can sort of assume that we have some
kind of a solution for inference. How to
perform order synchronous inference
using a time synchronous inf synchronous
inference mechanism. And so we'll refer
to the process of obtaining an output
from the network as decoding.
And so
here is what we have. We have come up
with some potentially hacky solution to
obtain order synchronous outputs. We did
this by actually generating times
synchronous outputs and then collapsing
repetitions.
This is in fact suboptimal.
It finds because we have we are actually
performing times synchronous and
inference. This inference finds the most
likely times synchronous output sequence
because you're producing you're picking
up the most like most probable symbol at
each time. This is not necessarily the
most likely order synchronous sequence.
We'll see that later in next class.
So thing to keep in mind is that this
process kind of makes sense. It's not
necessarily optimal.
So we have sort of partially addressed
the problem of
inference. How do we know when to output
symbols? And the way we did it, our
greedy solution was to pick the most
likely symbol at each time and simply
collapse repetitions. So, is everybody
good with this so far?
Yes or no?
Okay.
So the more interesting problem is how
do we train these models
and the simplest so that when you want
to train these models the data that you
can expect to get are input sequences
order not autosynchronous
od that's just my way of pronouncing it
okay that if you change the order of the
inputs the output the order of the
outputs changes in the same manner okay
so your training data are going to look
like this. You're going to get a
sequence of inputs and you're going to
get the order synchronous
sequence of outputs. So you might be
given the sequence of 10 vectors as
input and told that the output are these
three phone names B, O and T. And from
this you must train the model. Ideally
you would not merely be given these
symbols but you would also be told where
the symbols must be output. In other
words, you'd have information of this
kind that the input is this 10 vector
sequence and the desired output you must
output a bur at time two. You must
output an at time six. You must output a
T at time N.
If you have this kind of information
then training is simple and providing
this kind of information where you not
only provide the symbol but the exact
time at which the symbol must be output.
This is
what we refer to as providing the
alignment. Providing the time instant at
which each of these symbols must be
output actually aligns these output
symbol sequence with the input. It's
telling you that this is B, this is B
and this is T. So did the notion of an
alignment make sense
to all of you?
Right? And so in the ideal case you'll
be given not just the order synchronous
sequence but also the alignment which
means it will tell you exactly where
each output is to be generated. So this
is the notion of an alignment. The
timestamps of the output symbols give us
the alignment of the output sequence to
the input sequence. Which portion of the
input aligns to what symbol.
Simply knowing the output sequence
doesn't give you the alignment. If I
just told you that this is the this this
is the word but that doesn't tell you
where the you know which portion of the
input is b which portion is and which
portion is star. So the same symbol
sequence could be aligned to the input
in many different ways.
Knowing the symbol sequence does not
provide the alignment. The alignment is
extra information. That make sense to
everybody?
So this makes the fact okay
assuming you're given the alignment
which is to say you're given the input
sequence and the output sequence and
exactly where each of these symbols must
be on output. Then it's easy enough to
compute a divergence. You can simply
compute the output probability
distribution at this time compare it to
the symbol B. The output probability
distribution at time six compared to R.
The output probability distribution at
time 9 compare it to T. So you have
three KL divergences and the overall uh
divergence is the sum of these three KL
divergences.
But is this making
complete use of the input and the output
or can we do better? What do you guys
think? Can we do better than this?
How can we do better
anyone? So Edward, how would we do
better?
Copy for each sharp of time. Exactly
right. Beautiful. I can say that I know
this is B, but this B represents this
entire segment. So each of these must
also be B. This is an R, but this R
represents this entire segment. So each
of these must also be an R. And so on.
And so now my divergence becomes the sum
over all time
of the divergence between the actual
output of the network and the desired
output of the network which is simply
the same symbol repeated at each time.
And of course we know that if I use the
KL divergence, the KL divergence between
the output of the network which is a
probability vector and the desired
output of the network which is going to
be one hot which which has a one at only
the target symbol is simply going to be
the negative log probability assigned to
the target symbol by the network. And so
now the divergence that you're going to
have is the sum over all time of minus
of the log of the probability assigned
to the target symbol at each time by the
network. And so this divergence can now
be minimized to train the network. Did
this make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
This makes okay. Very good.
And so that's what we will do, right?
But what if this alignment was not
given?
What if we were we were given the output
sequence but we were not informed when
the output sequence must be generated.
This is a problem, right? We have data
insufficiency.
So can anybody suggest how I can go
about this?
I'm not given the output alignment. How
do I train the model?
Anybody?
We can ignore the outputs not selected.
Which outputs are not selected?
Guess.
So yes, we can guess the alignment. We
can start off with a guess. We can there
are two ways of going about it actually.
We can guess the alignment and then
train with the guest alignment or
you can consider all possible
alignments. These are the two options.
This make sense
over here.
Yes. Now
okay. Today we're going to look at this
solution.
Okay. Let's look at how. So what do you
mean by guessing the alignment? we can
somehow decide you know what the word is
you know beefy in my example and I'm
guessing that the bur must occur here
the e must occur here the firm must
occur here and the second e must occur
over here what that means is that these
this portion of the input according to
my guess is all b's this portion is all
e this portion is all fs and this is an
e so once I guess this initial alignment
I can use this alignment to train the
network. Once I've trained the network,
I can use this network to go back and
reestimate the alignment to improve it.
And the new the new reestimated
alignment may give me for example uh the
symbols in a completely different
location. It might say this time around
that the bur stays here but the e should
be here, the first should be here and
yeah the second e occurs over here.
Right? And now we have a new alignment.
You can go back and train the model
again with a new alignment and iterate
this process. So that make sense to
everybody
what we just did what I just said.
Okay, I have a single yes. Can I have a
go there? How do you reestimate the
alignment?
It has the guest and alignment. I've
trained a model with it. And now I'm
going to use this guest alignment to
reestimate the alignment. What is this
magical process of reestimating the
alignment for each training instance?
For that we have to go back and look at
what it means to align. The alignment
tells us which portion of the input
aligns to what symbol in the sequence.
So for example, if my output symbol
sequence is the phone sequence but B and
T, an alignment could say for example
that this portion of the input is all
for B. So the B must be out output at
the end of this this sequence this
section. This portion corresponds to so
the must be output at the end of this.
And this portion corresponds to T. The T
must be output at the end of this. And
as we saw earlier, you can have many
different ways of aligning the symbol
sequence to the input. I can make this
alignment more explicit by
uh actually repeating the symbol. So
when I say this entire sequence refers
to represents B, I can just repeat B and
so I have a sequence of BS. When I say
this entire sequence represents, I can
repeat us and have a sequence of us and
a sequence of ts. So each of these
alignments now gives me a sequence of
symbols.
What happened when I went from this
representation
to this one when I repeated each symbol?
What happened over here? Anybody think
in terms of synchrony? What happened?
Someone want to tell me
this is an order synchronous output.
Correct? Is this time synchronous? The
output over here
is not time synchronous. Right? When I
repeat things, my order synchronous
output sequence became a time
synchronous sequence. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes. No. Right. And so I can think of
this guy as a compressed version of this
guy where I performed the compression by
removing repetitions. And so also I can
think of this guy as an expanded version
of this guy where I expanded it by
repeating the symbol over the duration
that it represents. So did the notion of
compression and expansion make sense to
everybody?
Yes or no?
That make sense?
Okay.
And so the same asynchronous compressed
sequence can be expanded in many
different ways to align it to the input.
So also many different alignments could
all compress to the same compressed
sequence.
Either way the the mapping from the
compressed sequence to the expanded
aligned sequence is one to many and the
mapping from the aligned sequence to the
compressed sequence is many to one. So
now when I give you a compressed
sequence and ask it to ask you to find
the alignment, the actual question I'm
asking you is of all of these
alignments, which is the one that best
captures this guy. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes. No.
Okay. And so this is the problem. A
compressed sequence can have many
alignments.
We want to given the input data, we want
to find a specific alignment that is
most probable
for the compressed sequence. That's
what the problem of alignment actually
means. So given an unaligned klength
compressed symbol sequence s0 through
skus one like bp and an nl length input
where n is greater than k meaning the
input sequence is going from
x0 to xn minus one like in my example x0
to x and you're given a current trained
recurrent network. Remember we're using
this to reestimate the alignment. So you
already have a network that has been
trained. So given this compressed
sequence and the input sequence and the
current trained aligned sequence
recurrent network, we want to find the
alignment that is most probable. So in
other words, we want to find the times
synchronous sequence that is most
probable given the compressed sequence
and the input. So did this make sense?
You're given the input, you're given the
compressed sequence, you want to find
the time time synchronous sequence that
is most probable given these two guys.
So going back to what I have on the
previous slide, you're given the input,
you're you're given the input and you're
given this guy. So you're given X0, say
X0 through X9.
And you're given this guy
and you want to find out which of these
guys is most probable given these two.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Okay.
All right. And so this is the problem
that we're going to solve. Find the
time synchronous sequence that
compresses to the given
order synchronous sequence given the
input.
That leads us to our next hope.
Okay, man.
We'll get the answer shortly.
15 seconds, guys.
Five.
All right, let me end this.
Which of the statements are true?
1 2 3 4 5 Right. So yes, an order
synchronous symbol sequence that's
shorter than the input can be aligned to
the input by repeating symbols until the
expanded sequence is exactly as long as
the input. The alignment of an
autosynchronous symbol sequence to an
input is time synchronous. The symbol
sequence that's time synchronous to an
input can be compressed to a shorter
order synchronous sequence by
eliminating repetition. So
autosynchronous sequences are shorter
than the input, right? That are shorter
than the input are compressed simple
sequences. The alignment of course is
not unique.
So let's go back and go back to the
problem.
I'm going to consider this simple
example. I have no idea why I chose this
example, but I chose this many years ago
and I'm I've been suffering with it ever
since. So we have an
input sequence that's
nine vectors long in my example and the
compressed symbol sequence that have
that we have been given is B right I
want to find the alignment of B to this
input so let's say I choose a very
simple thing I already have the network
I pass the data through the network and
the network generates an output
probability vector
at each time. So now I just go through
this and pick the most probable symbol
at each time. If I just simply pick the
most probable symbol at each time,
am I going to get an alignment of the
word beefy to the input?
What do you think? Will I get why not?
Why not?
anyone? Why not?
Lots of unnecessary symbols, right? R is
not in B. Especially in the early
portions of your training, your
network's not going to be very good. So,
it might just find R to be the most
probable symbol over here. It's not even
part of B, right? It might find D to be
the most probable symbol here. It's not
part of B. So the symbols that you pick
may have nothing to do with the symbols
in the compressed symbol sequence that
you are trying to align the input to. So
given this,
can you think of a solution? How would I
fix this?
Any ideas? How would I fix this?
Anyone?
Some thoughts? One idea before I go.
Our problem is that if I just pick the
most likely symbol at each time, that
may have nothing to do with the symbols
in my target symbol sequence.
So how can I fix this?
Ignore unnecessary symbols. So I know
that I only have BV, right? So although
the network outputs entire probability
vectors at each time, I'm going to
ignore the the values corresponding to
all symbols that are not in my target
symbol sequence. That's going to leave
me only considering the probabilities of
B, E, and F.
And now I can work off these to align my
input to the uh target symbol sequence.
That make sense everybody?
Okay. And now on this I can go ahead. So
what the way I'm doing it is basically
starting off my with my large
probability table and I'm just picking
up the rows corresponding to bur and fur
and creating a reduced table which has
only these three guards. And so long as
I work only of this reduce table, I'm
not going to choose any unnecessary
symbols. And now I go ahead and pick the
most likely symbol from
this table at each time. Is this going
to be an alignment of my target symbol
sequence to the of my input to the
target symbol sequence?
Is this going to be a valid alignment?
Yes or no? No. Again, why not?
So not necessarily correct. But why not?
But what what's likely to happen?
It's not the symbols. Although you
choose the right symbols, this guy is
actually beefy. That's not beefy, right?
It's not ordered. The ordering is lost.
So although you're no longer
hypothesizing nonsensical symbols, the
order in which you get the symbols are
not necessarily going to correspond to
your target symbol sequence. That make
sense to everybody?
>> Yes or no?
>> Yes. Okay. So, can you suggest a
solution to this?
How would I fix this?
Anyone? How do I fix this?
Reorder.
That's a Anything else?
So,
I fix the order, right? And how do I fix
the order? Here's what I'm going to do.
Instead of simply con constructing a
table from only these symbols, I'm going
to construct the table, but I'm going to
do it in the order of my target symbols.
So my reduced table is now going to
because my compressed symbol sequence
has four symbols, my reduced table is
going to have four rows. The first row
is going to be this row of B's
probabilities assigned to B. The second
row is going to be the row of
probabilities assigned to E.
The third row is going to be the row of
probabilities assigned to F.
And then the fourth row is going to be
the row of probabilities assigned to E.
Here observe that although the network
has computed the probability of E only
once, when I copy these probabilities
into this modified reduced table, E, the
row for E has been copied twice.
Once for every instance of E in my
compressed symbol sequence.
This make sense what I just did
over here. Okay. So now what I'm going
to think of this probability as a table,
right? If a symbol occurs multiple
times, we repeat the row in the
appropriate location. So the row for E
occurs twice because E occurs in the
second and fourth positions in my
computer symbol sequence. And now I come
up with a simple rule, right? An
alignment is going to be a path that
goes from the top left entry of this
table to the bottom right entry of this
table following two simple rules. From
any position, I can either go directly
right or I can take one step down
diagonally. So if I do that, then the
kinds of paths that I'm going to have
are going to be things of this kind,
right? or maybe something of this kind.
But the guarantee that I have in this
process is that I'm going to have a
sequence of B's followed by a sequence
of E followed by a sequence of Fs and
followed by a sequence of E again. And
the overall length is going to be
exactly the same as the same as the
length of the input sequence. And so
every path from this top left node to
the bottom right node that follows these
rules that at any time you can either
take a step right or you can take take
one step diagonally down. Every path of
this kind is a valid alignment of beefy
to the input.
That making sense to everybody?
So maybe this is key. And maybe I can
see like 25 yeses.
I have seven. So give humor me guys.
It's after spring break. Give me 25.
They're struggling at 15.
Come on.
Do I give up?
Okay.
15. We maxed out at 15. 16. Guys, this
is this is sad. do better the next time
I ask. So this is what we're going to
do, right? Every path from the top left
to the bottom right that follows these
rules is a valid alignment of the symbol
sequence to the input. I can reccast
this as a graph problem. From every
node, I can think of every one of these
cells as a node in a graph. And from
every node I can draw an edge which is
either hor one edge that's horizontal
and another edge that goes immediately
down diagonally. So now this is a graph
and every path through this graph
represents a valid alignment of my
target symbol sequence to the input.
Why? Because every path through this
graph is going to have is going to have
a sequence of furs a sequence of ease
sequence of furs and then and a sequence
of ease in that order which is an
alignment of B to the input. That make
sense?
Yes. No.
And
so now if I want to pick the best
alignment,
I want to pick the best path through
this graph.
But to define the best, what do you mean
by the best? I want to pick the path
that represents the most probable
alignment.
In order to do that, I'm going to assign
probabilities.
Every node over here is going to be
given a probability, which is basically
the probability assigned to the symbol
represented by the node at the time
represented by the node. So this node
over here carries the probability to
assigned to the symbol B at time zero by
the network. This node over here is
going to carry the probability assigned
to the symbol F at time 4 by the
network. And so that's how we're going
to populate
the probabilities of all the nodes in
the graph. The edges are all going to be
assigned a probability of one. So now
when I go through this graph and compute
the probability of the path it
represents all I will do is to multiply
the probabilities of all the nodes on
the path and that is going to give me
the probability of that alignment to the
input. That make sense?
Yes. No.
Right. So which path would I choose
in this case?
Which path would I choose of all the
paths?
Anybody?
Come on guys, I've told you a way of
scoring the paths. Which path would I
choose?
Computer science majors.
Find the highest probability path. I'm
going to find the path that has the
highest score where the score of a path
is simply the the product of the
probabilities of all the nodes on the
path or alternately the sum of the log
path.
So
the score of any path is simply going to
be the product of all these
probabilities. So if I take a partial
part like this guy, the score of this
part is going to be this product of this
probability. This one, this one, this
one, and this one. And if I have a
complete path from end to end, the score
of that path is going to be the product
of the probabilities of all the nodes in
the path.
There's an exponential number of such
paths. And our challenge is to find the
path for which this probability is
highest.
This is a graph search problem. I want
to find the path through the graph that
has the highest score. Does this make
sense to everybody?
Yes. Now, how would you solve it?
Computer science majors must find this
to be a breeze, right? How would I solve
this?
Greedy. Well, greedy give me the five
best
Dystra depth first search. Right? So, we
have any number of algorithms that will
find you the best path from a source to
a sync because this is a directed
asyclic graph. All paths start from
here. All paths end from here. It's a
directed asyclic graph. We can have a
star. But in this kind of graph where
every path is exactly the same length,
what kind of algorithm would be most
efficient? Depth first or bread first?
What do you guys think?
Which is going to be most efficient?
DFS. BFS.
It's going to be breath first because
breath first is going to be
deterministic in its computation. The
so-called so you're going to find the
most probable python source to sync. You
can use any dynamic programming
algorithm. The one that we normally use
is breath first search which is the
vitby algorithm. Right? So what is the
idea behind the vby? So did everything I
say so far make sense? how we composed
the graph and then how we found
converted the problem of finding the
best alignment to a graph search
problem. That makes sense to everybody.
Yes. Right. And so how we do this? Now
consider the best path from the source
to this node. If I want to find the best
path from the source to this node, this
node has only two parents.
paths to this node can come either from
here or from here. There's no because it
has only two incoming edges. So this
means that the best path from the source
to this node must either come from this
parent or come from this parent. Does
that make sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Okay. So now if I consider this
parent over here, right?
Let's say I consider this parent and
some magically some oracle magic told me
magically that the best path comes
through this pair. So is the best path
through this parent to this node likely
to be an extension of the second best
path to this guy or is always going to
be an extension of the best path to this
guy to this node? What do you think? Can
the second best path to this node
be extended to this guy and have a
higher overall score than the best path
to this node being extended here?
It always has to be an extension of the
best path, right? Because the second
best path, guess what? It's second best.
Any extension is going to keep it lower
than the best path. So which means that
the best path to this node is either an
extension of the best path to this node
or an extension of the best path to this
node. That make sense to everybody?
Yes. No.
Right.
Very simple. Right. So what is this?
That leads me to this very simple
algorithm.
At each point
for each node
I will pick the best parent. And the way
I pick the best parent is I'm going to
pick the parent for which the best path
score is higher. So each of these
parents has a best path coming to it. So
I will look at the best path score to
this node and the best path score to
this node and pick the node for which
the best path score is highest and say
that is my best parent and extend it.
Why? Because if the best path score to
this guy is lower than the best path
score to this guy, extending this can
only result in a lower score than
extended extending this guy. Right? And
so all I will do is look at all of my
parents, pick the parent which has the
which has the highest best path score
and then extend it. That make sense to
every the logic?
Does logic make make sense to everybody?
Right? Very simple, right? So the best
parent is always the parent of the best
path best scoring best path. You're
going to go over all the parents. Pick
the parent for which the best path score
is highest and then you're going to
extend it to the current node. So that
leads us to this very simple algorithm.
Right? I'm going going going to
dynamically track the best path and the
score of the best path from the source
node to every node in the graph. At each
node, I'm going to keep track of the
best incoming parentage, the score of
the best path from the source to the
node through this best parentage and
eventually compute the best path from
source to sync. It's this looks like a
lot of text. Uh let's look at it a
little more pictorially. Just
introducing some notation first.
I'm going to use the symbol y
superscript subscript. The subscript
represents the time. The superscript
represents the symbol. When I say s of r
is the symbol in the r row. So s of0 is
the symbol in the zero row which is b. S
of one is the symbol in the first row
which is e. s of two is the symbol in
the second row which is f. S of three is
the symbol on the third row which is
three. This did this did this notation
and this one make sense to everybody.
Okay. Right. And so here is my
algorithm. Very simple.
I'm going to start off at the left node
and I'm left most column and I say these
are the first column. They have no
parents. So all of them have no parent.
The parent is none. The best path score
to this guy
is just the best path score from the
beginning to this guy is simply this
node score because this is the entire
path. The best path score to these guys
is all zero are all zero because no path
can begin from these three locations.
That make sense?
Yes. No. Okay. That's for the first
column. I will start at the first
column. Then having filled up the best
path score for each of these guys, I go
to the second column. In the second
column, for each node, I consider all of
it parents. And then I pick the parent
for which the best path score was
highest. And I keep track of the
identity of the best parent. And then so
I I keep track of the identity of the
best parent. And then I say the best
path score to this node is the
probability the best path probability
for the best parent multiplied by the
node score itself because I've extended
the path to here. This make sense to
everybody.
Can I see if like a dozen yeses before I
proceed?
like four. Come on. That's any like I'm
not asking for 25. I'm asking for 12.
And I'm not running into double digits.
So the guys who didn't get it
guys, I asked for 12, I got 10.
Maybe I'll ask for zero. That way I'm
going to get get it every time. Okay. Uh
all right. So this is the basic
algorithm. So here's what it is. Uh
I start off my algorithm goes left to
right. Starts at the first column and
goes all the way. In the first column
I'm going to say the best parent to all
of my nodes is null because they have no
parent. The best path score to this guy
is simply
the probability assigned to this symbol
at time zero by the network. Y0 s0. The
best path scores to these guys are all
zero. Then subsequently I go to the next
time instant. If I start from the top,
the top one, it has only one parent. So
the best parent must be this guy. So I
can just copy it over. The best parent
is zero. And the best path score to this
guy is going to be the best path score
at time t minus one because this is at
time t, right? at t minus one
uh to the zeroth node multiplied by the
node probability of this guy itself. So
did this make sense? Why I make a
special case for the top row? I don't
need to but the top row has only one
parent. That make sense
to everybody?
Okay. And now I go to the second one.
The second one has two parents.
This parent has a best path score. This
parent also has a best path score. And
that there are two parents in the L row.
The two parents are L, which is the same
row earlier, and L minus one, which is
the previous row earlier. Right? And so
I'm going to look at the best path
scores at both row L and L minus one at
time T minus one and pick the one for
for which this best path score was
largest. And I'm going to assign my best
parent as this a as the one for which
the best path score was largest. And
then I say the best path score to the
node itself is going to be the best path
score to the parent times the known
score. And so now for this node I have I
know the identity of the best parent and
the best path score to the node. So I
can do that for go down the column and I
can do that for all the nodes in this
column. Of course, the best path score
to these two guys is going to be zero
because all their parents have zero
score. Having done this for this row,
then I move on to the next row. For each
node, the first node of course has only
one parent. But subsequently, every node
has multiple parents where which can be
either
the same time L which can be the same
row L or L minus one. And I pick the
parent which has the highest best bat
score. keep track of that parent and
then extend the best path score to the
best parent to the current node by
multiplying the node score. I go down
the column do this for all the nodes in
the column. Of course, over here this
guy's going to get a zero score. And now
at this time I know not only the best
parent to every node but also the best
fat score to every node. I do this next
to all the nodes in the next column
where I go down find the best parent and
find the best bat score and keep doing
this all the way till I get to the end.
That make sense?
This is this is this basic depth first
search. Did this make sense to
everybody? And now can I get like a
dozen yeses?
F3 four.
Guys, don't be stingy with your yeses.
Okay, good. Thank you. So once I do
this, I know that the final symbol must
be this guy, correct?
For this guy, I know the best parent. I
stored it for that guy. I know the best
parent because I stored it going back.
And so I can trace the best parents all
the way to the beginning to get the best
overall path through the graph.
That make sense to everybody?
Starting from t minus one, I go down and
I keep picking the best parent and
that's going to give me the most likely
overall alignment of the input of the
symbol sequence to the input.
Did this make sense?
Okay, if it made sense, give me a thumbs
up and I'll wait for a dozen.
Okay. Oh, good. I got 30. Good.
So, here's your final point.
Okay.
15 seconds, guys.
Okay, let me end this
and can can somebody give me tell me
which statements are true?
Which statements are true? One and two.
Right. Again, Adita. So
decoding finds the most probable
alignment of a compressed sequence to an
input. It's run on a table of
probabilities constructed for the
compressed sequence with one row for
each symbol in the sequence derived from
the probability table generated by the
output of the recurren network. Adita
did that answer your question?
Good. Okay. And so here we are right
here's what I have some pseudo code for
it. I will uh just
assuming that you know you've run the
neural network. So the neural network is
going to be generating this table of
probabilities y at each time. So from
those you can create the compressed
uh the reduced table. And this little
pseudo code here is just actually
capturing the uh litterb alignment. I'll
I'll skip the pseudo code. Please look
it up. The end result is going to be an
alignment, a guest alignment using the
current model.
So the current model and the input
together
uh the current model, the input and the
target sequence are all used together to
obtain the best alignment of this target
sequence to the input. That's going to
give me give you a time synchronous
symbol sequence. And now once you have a
time synchronous symbol sequence, what
can you do with this guys? What can you
do with this?
Anybody?
Come on. This is easy.
Compute the divergence. Right? The
divergence is simply going to be the sum
over all time of the kale divergence
between the symbol in the aligned
sequence and the output probability
computed by the network which is going
to be have as many probabilities as the
as the vocabulary
and but if I choose the kale divergence
the kale divergence simply becomes the
negative log probability assigned to
this target symbol and so the divergence
itself now simply becomes minus of the
sum over time of the log of the
probability assigned
to the symbols in this aligned sequence
by the network. So did this make sense?
Yes or no?
That make sense to everybody? Okay.
Kless cross entropy, right? We saw that
if you're using one hot encoding care is
cross entropy and cross entropy simply
becomes minus of the log probability
assigned to the target symbol. And of
course when you take the derivative of
this divergence with respect to the
output of the network at any time you
only need to comp consider
the
probability assigned to the symbol at
that time by the network. You can ignore
the rest of time. Right? So the
derivative of with respect to any y of t
this derivative is going to have as many
components as the vocabulary over which
you're performing inference.
But then because the divergence itself
only invokes the log probability of the
target symbol the d the rest of the
derivative terms are going to be zero.
And for the target symbol alone, the
component corresponding to the target
symbol alone, the divergence is going
the derivative of the divergence is
going to be minus1 over the probability
assigned to that uh symbol simply
because the derivative of log of y is 1
/ one. Did this make sense?
So you could have 500 phonms in your
vocabulary,
but
at time zero
the target symbol is B. So which means
the derivative is going to have zeros
everywhere and it's going to have 1 /
minus one over the probability assigned
to B at time zero in the location of B.
Right? That's it. And so once you have
this then you can use this tool. you can
back propagate these derivatives and
train the network. So the overall
procedure is you're going to initialize
your alignment. Then you're going to
train your model with the given
alignments. Then these model given
alignments are going to be used for WB
alignment also called WB decoding by the
way to obtain updated alignments. So
what is the what is your best guess for
the alignment given this model and the
input? You do this, you update the
alignments for for your inputs and use
the updated alignments to go back and
retrain the model. And you keep doing
this until the whole thing converges. So
here this align and train steps can be
combined into a single align you know uh
find alignment and compute derivative
steps for SGD. So within each mini batch
you can keep updating the model and for
each input instance you can
simultaneously find the alignment and
the derivatives within back propagation.
So did this whole process make sense
guys?
Yes. No. Okay.
And so there are different ways of doing
it. You can determine the alignment for
the entire training data and then train
the model or during SGD for each
training instance you find the alignment
during the forward pass and then using
the backward pass. It all works. The
problem here is that
you're guessing alignments. So the
approach is heavily dependent on the
initial alignment. If your initial guess
is pathetic, your model is going to go
into poor local optimum. And more
generally if the amount of training data
you have is not very if the training
data becomes very large then the errors
can sometimes somewhat can cancel out
and the whole thing would work.
Otherwise your initial guess for an
alignment can end up giving you poor
initial models and those poor initial
models are going to give you poor
reestimated alignments and the whole
process can go into a local optimum. And
so a better thing to do is to train
without explicit alignment. This is what
we call the connectionist temporary
classification framework. We'll do this
see this in the next class and also talk
about separating repeated symbols and
the CTC decoder. So did the whole
lecture make sense? So
did the lecture make sense? everything
for today
and I'll stop the recording.